Omkar Raut

(+1) 980-327-8262 | omkarraut33@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/raut-omkar | rautomkar.medium.com | raut-omkar.github.io | github.com/raut-omkar

SUMMARY

A cybersecurity consultant with 3 years of experience, who reduced security risk by 70% through implementing security measures, is now seeking a rewarding career in their area of specialization to utilize their full potential and contribute to the company's long-term growth.

EXPERIENCE

Amazon

Security Engineer Intern

05/2022 to 08/2022

Seattle, USA

- Devised a framework using Graph Database and data visualization to speed up and increase the accuracy of analysis for complex, multi-dimensional datasets by 80% while also increasing the accuracy of the analysis results by 50%.
- Evaluated high-severity tactics and techniques from MITRE attacks and categorized them against AWS services, improving remediation time by 50% and enhancing the organization's security posture.
- Mapped 250+ AWS Security Hub Controls to the different techniques and tactics, and gained insights into various AWS services.
- Reduced the time to identify attacks, and implement mitigations by 80% for internal security teams and developers.

Associate Security Consultant

11/2019 - 08/2021

Varutra Consulting Pvt. Ltd.

Pune, India

- Adapted to conduct web, network, mobile, APIs, and thick client vulnerability assessment and penetration testing.
- Discovered over 100 vulnerabilities and mitigated in the client's infrastructure with a possible impact of \$50 million and considerably more.
- Conducted DAST/SAST, ethical hacking, and expertise in exploiting vulnerabilities such as XSS, CSRF, SSRF, Broken Access Control, SQL Injection, Privilege Escalation, XXE, and so on.
- Performed client and server side attacks, enhanced and secured clients' infrastructure, resulting in \$3M savings across multiple applications in banking, finance, healthcare, and software industries.
- Managed over 30 clients and Implemented security enhancements to the apps, development, and production environments by collaborating with developers and system administrators.
- Reported vulnerabilities in a comprehensible document based on their severity and CVSS score, resulting in a 60% decrease in the likelihood of cyber attacks.

Associate Security Analyst

11/2018 - 10/2019

GFI Informatique India

Pune, India

- Monitored and analyzed daily network traffic using LogRhythm SIEM and IDS/IPS tools, detecting and responding to over 500 security incidents, and IOCs per month, and produced 50+ actionable threat intelligence reports.
- Investigated the source of malicious network traffic, detecting and blocking 500+ malicious IPs, domains, and URLs; Blacklisted 100+ malicious hashes, mitigating the risk of future attacks.
- Created monthly trend analysis, and risk assessment reports utilizing bar graphs and pie charts, resulting in a 40% improvement in the organization's incident response time and a 25% decrease in overall risk exposure.
- Coordinated with customers to provide real-time advice on network configuration, access controls, policies, and attack mitigation procedures, reduced escalation and resolution times by 70% resulting in a \$50 million cost savings.

EDUCATION

University of North Carolina at Charlotte

Master of Science, Cybersecurity, GPA - 4.0/4.0

RMD Sinhgad School Of Engineering

Bachelor of Engineering, IT, GPA - 3.5/4.0

Charlotte, NC 08/2021 to 05/2023
Pune, India 06/2015 to 05/2018

SKILLS

Languages: Java, Python, C/C++, SQL,HTML/CSS

Security Frameworks: OWASP TOP 10, NIST, OSINT, SANS 25

Tools/OS: Burp Suite, OWASP Zap Proxy, Nmap, Nessus, Nexpose, SQLmap, Metasploit, Wireshark, Shodan, Nikto, Acunetix, Netsparker, MobSF, Postman, Echo Mirage Hijacker, Frida, Widows, Kali Linux

CERTIFICATIONS

CEH - Certified Ethical Hacker

OSCP- In Progress

Certified Network Security Specialist